Slow Cooker Chinese Beef and Bok Choy

Food Network Magazine 2015

Ingredients:

4 leeks; use the white and light green parts. Trim them, cut in half lengthwise, rinse very well! then chop into 1 inch pieces.

6 cloves garlic, unpeeled, washed

4 thin slices fresh ginger, unpeeled, washed

1 red jalapeno pepper, seeded and thinly sliced (or can use 1/8 teaspoon dried crushed red pepper flakes, or to taste)

3 tablespoons all purpose flour

3 lb beef chuck roast, trimmed

1/4 cup hoisin sauce

1/4 cup rice wine, mirin, dry sherry or sake

3 tablespoons soy sauce

2 tablespoons packed light brown sugar

4 heads baby bok choy, cut crosswise into 2 inch pieces

1/3 cup warm water

2 cups cooked rice for serving

Preparation:

Put the leeks, garlic, ginger and pepper in the slow cooker (recipe designed for a 7-quart pot).

Add the flour and toss to combine.

Place the meat on top of the vegetables.

Combine the hoisin sauce,rice wine,soy sauce, brown sugar and 1/3 cup warm water in a bowl, and pour that over the meat.

Cook it on low for 7 1/2 hours, then remove the meat,and slice it thinly against the grain.

Take out and discard the garlics and gingers.

Put the meat back in the pot and add the bok choy on top of it.

Turn the slow cooker to high and let cook for about 5 minutes, till bok choy is wilting. Serve over rice.

Spagetti Sauce

Ingredients

1 yellow onion, diced

1 green or red bell pepper, diced

garlic, 2 to 3 cloves, crushed and peeled

Carrots, 2 medium, diced

Olive oil

28 ounce can tomato sauce

28 ounce can tomato puree

dried basil (a spoonful or two0

dried oregano (a spoonful or two)

dried red pepper flakes (a pinch)

ground black pepper

sugar or brown sugar (a teaspoon or so)

1 pound ground turkey or chicken or lean beef

Optional: diced pepperoni

1. Make sofrito with olive oil, onion and bell pepper in big pot; saute over medium heat till onion is translucent, about 5 minutes.

2. Add carrot and garlic to sofrito for 2 or 3 minutes, taking care to not burn the garlic.

3. In another pan,fry the meat till it is no longer pink; drain grease from pan, or scoop meat out with slotted spoon.

4. Add the two cans of tomatoes, spices, and ground meat to the pot.

5. You may need to add a can or two of water to dilute the sauce.

6. Bring to boil, then decrease heat to low and cook, partially covered with lid, for 2 to 3 hours. Check to see if you need to add more water.

7. Serve with spagetti noodles.

Pearl Millet Porridge(Bajra Khichdi) by: Nandita (Saffron Trail)

INGREDIENTS

2/3 cup pearl millet bajra

1/3 cup moong dal

2 tsp ghee or coconut oil

1 tsp cumin seeds

4 cloves garlic finely chopped

2 medium potatoes peeled and quartered

1 medium carrot cut into chunks

1 large tomato quartered

2-3 green chillies slit

1 tsp salt

1/2 tsp turmeric powder

1 tbsp coriander powder

1 tsp garam masala powder

2 cups finely chopped spinach

INSTRUCTIONS

To prepare the pearl millet khichdi / bajra khichdi, soak the millet for at least 12 hours in water. This step is mandatory.

Wash moong dal. Drain and keep aside. Drain water from the millet just before preparing the khichdi.

Heat ghee in a pressure pan (~3-5 Litre capacity). Fry cumin seeds, garlic, chillies and vegetables for a minute.

Add the drained millet and moong dal along with all the dried spices and salt. Mix 4.5 cups water into this and bring to a boil.

Lock the cooker lid with the pressure weight plugged in. After 3 whistles, reduce flame to sim and cook for 15-20 minutes. (Because of this long cooking on slow flame, it is important to add more than adequate water to the khichdi otherwise it will burn and stick to the bottom of the cooker. Beginner cooks can also transfer the entire mix with the water into another vessel that fits inside the cooker. Keep 1.5 inches of water in the bottom of the cooker. Mix in 4 cups water to the millet-dal-veg mix in the vessel and cook similarly, or possibly for 5 minutes longer on sim (20 mins after 3 whistles).)

Once the pressure subsides, open cooker and stir in the finely chopped spinach into the khichdi. Keep covered for 5-10 minutes so the spinach cooks in the residual heat. You will know that the pearl millet is cooked on tasting or if the grains have broken open.

Serve this hot along with roasted papads and sliced cucumber. Pickles and yogurt optional.

NOTES Prepare the same khichdi using any other whole grain like foxtail millet, brown rice or quinoa. Use any seasonal vegetables like beans, sweet potatoes, green peas, pumpkin and a mix of any seasonal green leafy vegetables.

Pearl Millet In Indian Languages Tamil – Kambu Hindi / Bengali / Odia / Punjabi – Bajra Kannada – Sajje Gujarati / Marathi – Bajri Telugu – Sajja

PEARL MILLET RECIPES | SAVOURY PEARL MILLET PORRIDGE | BAJRA KHICHDI JULY 24, 2019

One Pot Meal Pearl millet (bajra) khichdi recipe prepared with moong dal and vegetables is almost like a risotto in texture. You cannot overcook pearl millet as it retains its texture very well, despite cooking for a long time. Do not mistake the chewy texture for uncooked/improperly cooked millet. When adding vegetables to the khichdi, cut into large chunks because of the overall increased cooking time.

Once you have soaked the millets for 12 hours, this makes an easy weeknight dinner. The khichdi cooks in the pressure cooker while you go about other chores. A plate of hot khichdi with your favourite accompaniments makes a comforting meal like no other on a nippy evening. This pearl millet recipe needs overnight prep in terms of soaking. That apart, this gluten free grain combined with mung dal and vegetables, makes a wholesome healthy meal. It is also an excellent recipe for diabetics.

Want to add more whole grains in your diet for their excellent health benefits?

This is one grain (high fibre, high protein, gluten free) that you must consider adding to your pantry.

Pearl Millet In Indian Languages Tamil – Kambu Hindi / Bengali / Odia / Punjabi – Bajra Kannada – Sajje Gujarati / Marathi – Bajri Telugu – Sajja Pearl Millet or whole bajra is an excellent whole grain to stock up in the kitchen. A lot of cooks get discouraged by the very long cooking time, labelling it difficult to cook.

It is best to soak any whole grain before proceeding to cook with it. This applies to pearl millet too.

Soaking reduces the anti-nutrient ‘phytic acid’ that is present in the outer cover of the grains. Soaking, sprouting or fermenting are the three techniques that must be used with whole grains to ensure that maximum nutrients are absorbed by the body.

Eating Pearl Millet – For Diabetics And Weight Loss Pearl Millet is an excellent grain for diabetics due to its high fibre content. The carbohydrates get converted into glucose and released into the blood stream in a more gradual manner, preventing any spikes in blood sugar.

The fibre also gives a sense of fullness for a longer period after a meal with a relatively smaller portion of food making it a very good option for those attempting to lose weight.

How To Cook Pearl Millet Or Bajra A tough grain like pearl millet does good with a long soaking time – a minimum of 12 hours. Drain the water and pressure cook with 3-4 times the water for at least 15-20 mins (after full pressure / whistle). Cooker larger quantities at one time and refrigerate to use in other recipes to save on time and effort. Pearl millet flour / bajra atta is used in some cuisines in India to prepare flatbreads – Gujarat / Rajasthan mainly, because of the arid climate that favours growth of this millet. Bajra is traditionally eaten in the winters because it is seen as a ‘warming food’ and not advocated for the summer diet.

Thai Red Curry with Shrimp, Vegetables, and Infused Rice

Author Molly | Spices in My DNA

Ingredients

For the infused rice

1 3/4 cups water

1 cup basmati or Jasmine rice

3 cardamom pods, crushed with the back of a knife*

2 star anise pods*

1/2 teaspoon salt

For the curry

1 tablespoon coconut oil

3 cloves garlic, finely chopped

1 tablespoon freshly grated ginger

2 scallions, thinly sliced

1 medium shallot, thinly sliced

1/4 cup Thai red curry paste*

2 (14.5 ounce) cans full-fat coconut milk*

1/2 teaspoon salt

1/4 teaspoon pepper

1 pound large shrimp, peeled and deveined

1 yellow bell pepper, very thinly sliced

1 small-medium broccoli crown, cut into small florets (or, summer squash or bamboo shoots, or mushrooms, or zucchini…)

2 large carrots, shaved into ribbons with a vegetable peeler

zest of 1 lime

juice of 1 lime

1 tablespoon soy sauce

1/4 cup chopped cilantro, plus extra for serving

thai basil for serving*

thinly sliced scallions for serving

lime wedges for serving

Instructions

Begin by making the rice. Bring the water to a boil in a medium saucepan (that has a lid). Once boiling, add the rice, cardamom pods, star ansie pods, and salt. Stir to combine. Cover and reduce heat to medium-low. Cook for 15-20 minutes, or until all liquid is absorbed and rice is tender. Fluff with a fork and discard cardamom and star anise pods.

While the rice is cooking, make the curry. Heat a large, deep skillet over medium-high heat. Add the coconut oil. Once hot, add the garlic, ginger, and a pinch of salt and sauté for 30 seconds to 1 minute, or until fragrant. Add the scallions and shallot and sauté for another 2 minutes. Add the curry paste and cook for an additional 1-2 minutes, stirring constantly to prevent it from burning.

Add the coconut milk, salt, and pepper. Increase heat to high and bring to a boil. Once boiling, add the shrimp, bell pepper, broccoli, and carrots. Reduce heat slightly and simmer for 2-3 minutes, or until shrimp are cooked through and vegetables are cooked to your liking.

Remove from heat, let cool for a minute or two, and stir in lime zest, lime juice, soy sauce, and chopped cilantro. Season to taste with additional salt and pepper if desired. Serve the curry over the infused rice, and garnish with extra cilantro, Thai basil, and scallions. Serve with lime wedges.

Recipe Notes

*Prep Time 20 minutes *Cook Time 20 minutes *Servings 4 *Sometimes cardamom pods can be trickier to find, depending on your grocery store. These are what I use when I can't find them at the store. Whole Foods usually has them too! *Same goes for star anise pods. I get them here when I can't get them at the grocery store. *Make sure you use full-fat coconut milk here. The “lite” stuff isn't nearly as good, especially for this type of curry.

Southern Black-eyed Peas Ingredients:

1 pound (453 gms) dry black-eyed peas

4-5 thick slices of (turkey) bacon

1 cup smoked sausage or turkey, diced

1 large onion, diced

2-3 teaspoons minced garlic

1 jalapeno, minced, or replace with cayenne pepper (optional)

2 teaspoons fresh thyme, minced

1 bay leaf

1-2 teaspoons creole or cajun seasoning

7-8 cups chicken broth

2 cups or more chopped collard greens or kale (optional)

salt and pepper to taste.\

Rinse black-eyed peas, pick out any rocks, and add to large pot, covering them with 3-4 inches of cold water. Cover and let sit for 2-3 hours.

In a large heavy saute pan, saute chopped bacon until brown and crispy, about 4-5 minutes, then add sausage and saute for 2-3 more minutes. Remove and set aside.

Add the onions, garlic, jalapenos, thyme and bay leaf, and saute for about 3-5 minutes, until onions are wilted and aromatic.

Pour in the chicken broth or water.

Drain the soaked beans, rinse, and place beans in the pot. Season with creole seasoning and salt to taste. Mix and bring to a boil.

Reduce heat to a simmer and cook, uncovered, about 20 minutes.

Add collard greens, bacon and sausage into the pot, continue cooking for about 10 minutes or more, stirring occasionally or until beans are tender and slightly thickened.

Add more stock or water if the mixture becomes dry or thick; the texture of the beans should be thick, somewhat creamy but not watery.

Remove the bay leaf.

Taste and adjust seasoning. Serve over cooked rice and garnish with green onion.

www.africanbites.com

Merlin's Magic Sourdough Bread (2 large loaves)

Ingredients

1 cup (227 gm) sourdough starter, ripe (fed)

1 2/3 cups (379 gm) warm water

5 1/2 cups (659 gm) King Arthur Unbleached All-Purpose flour (or mixture of all-purpose and bread flour)

1 1/2 teaspoons active dry yeast or instant yeast

2 teaspoons salt

2 tablespoons (25 gm) olive oil

Instructions

The day before; mix starter, water, and 3 cups of the flour(362 gm). Cover with a damp towel, and let this sponge sit at room temperature for 2 hours; then refrigerate overnight, or for up to 16 hours.

The next day: add the yeast, salt, oil, and enough of the remaining 2 1/2 cups flour to make a soft dough that cleans the sides of the bowl. Turn the dough out onto a lightly floured or oiled work surface, snd knead it for at least 10 minutes, adding more flour as necessary, until it is smooth and springs back when you poke it. If the dough feels too stiff, add a few more teaspoons of water to soften it.

Place the dough in a lightly greased bowl, cover it with lightly greased plastic wrap, and let it rise for 2 hours at moderate room temperature (below 80F or so). The dough should become puffy.

Press the dough down and divide it into two pieces. Form each piece into a round ball, and place each ball on a baking sheet that has been greased and sprinkled with cornmeal. Cove the loaves with damp towels or lightly greased plastic wrap, and allow them to rise fr 1 hour or longer until they've become puffy and a pressed finger leaves a mark.

While loaves are rising, preheat the oven to 425F.

Bake for about 25 to 30 minutes, until the bread is golden, sounds hollow when tapped, and internal temperature is 190F to 205F on a digital thermometer.

Remove bread from the oven and cool completely on a rack.

Store loosely wrapped for 3 days, or wrap tightly and freeze for up to 3 months.

Stuffed Mushrooms By Kay Chun YIELD4 servings TIME25 minutes

These fun hors d’oeuvres turn humble mushrooms into rich, savory bites with the flavors of escargots, the classic French delicacy of snails cooked in garlic butter. Here, fragrant and buttery bread crumbs infused with garlic, shallots and parsley fill mushroom caps. The roasted cremini mushrooms emerge from the oven juicy, with a garlicky topping that’s golden and crispy. Make use of your trimmings: The mushroom stems can be frozen for later use in vegetable or chicken stock.

INGREDIENTS

4 tablespoons unsalted butter, at room temperature

2 tablespoons finely chopped parsley

1 tablespoon minced shallot

2 teaspoons minced garlic

Kosher salt and black pepper

½ cup plain panko bread crumbs

2 dozen small cremini mushrooms (about 1 pound), stemmed

2 tablespoons extra-virgin olive oil

PREPARATION

Heat oven to 425 degrees. In a small bowl, combine butter, parsley, shallot and garlic; season with salt and pepper. Stir in bread crumbs until well combined.

On a baking sheet, drizzle mushrooms with oil, season with salt and pepper, and toss to evenly coat. Arrange mushrooms cavity-side up and spoon a heaping 1/2 teaspoon of the bread crumb mixture into each.

Bake until mushrooms are tender and bread crumbs are golden and crispy, about 15 minutes. Serve warm.

Broccoli cheddar soup

Yield: 6 servings I made this for my QVS house of 6 people and doubled the recipe, we had some leftovers but definitely not 6 servings worth of leftovers.

Total time: 30-50 minutes

Ingredients:

1/4 cup butter

1/2 medium chopped onion

1/4 cup flour

2 cups chicken or veggie stock/broth

2 cups half and half cream

1/2 lb broccoli (about 3 cups) chopped into bite size pieces

1 cup carrot, julienned (matchstick carrots)

1/4 tsp nutmeg, optional

8oz grated sharp cheddar cheese (2 cups)

salt and pepper

Instructions:

Melt butter and sauté onions until soft. Sprinkle flour over the mixture and cook over medium heat, stirring, for 1-2 minutes.

Whisk in the half & half and the broth.

Add broccoli and carrots. Cook over low heat for 20-25 mins or until veggies are tender

Add salt and pepper to taste.

Blend about 1 cup of soup and stir it back in for a smoother soup. Keep on low heat and add cheese. Stir in additional spices if desired.

Best served with bread!

Notes:

When I doubled the recipe I ran out of cream so used 2 cups half and half and 2 cups whole milk. Came out fine, didn't really notice.

Would chop the broccoli a little smaller next time.

Have never used the nutmeg. Might be good?